<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Confutation of sundry errors in Dr. Sherlock's book concerning allegiance</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34269</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5812</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20781</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12259465</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12259465</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57786</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34269)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57786)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 177:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Confutation of sundry errors in Dr. Sherlock's book concerning allegiance</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sherlock, William, 1641?-1707. --  Case of the allegiance due to soveraign powers.</term>
               <term>Allegiance.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="confutation">
            <pb facs="tcp:57786:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57786:1"/>
            <head>A Confutation of ſundry Errors in Dr. <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi>'s Book concerning Allegiance.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 1. <q>THE Scripture hath given us no Directions in this Caſe, but to ſubmit, and pay all the Obedience of Subjects to the preſent Powers. It makes no diſtinction, that ever I could find, between rightful Kings and Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, <bibl>
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 18.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> Why then did you ſtand off ſo long from ſwearing Allegiance to their preſent Majeſties, out of ſcruple of Conſcience? And why do you condemn <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> and the Rump-Parliament, and the late <hi>Inter-regnum</hi> as a Rebellion? And why do you approve the Peoples Combination againſt, and killing <hi>Athaliah</hi> as an Uſurper, and ſetting young <hi>Joaſh,</hi> the right Heir, in the Throne? To ſay that there is no difference as to our Duty and Allegiance between a manifeſt Uſurper, and a manifeſt rightful Owner of the Crown, is in effect to ſay, that a manifeſt Uſurper is not an Uſurper; which is a Contradiction. The Scripture largely taken, doth comprize the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Natural Religion, and all the Rules and Maxims of Order, Government, and Civil Society common to Chriſtians and Heathens, who all agree in this, That there are two ſorts of Kings, a manifeſt U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurper, and a manifeſt rightful Owner of the Crown; and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there are two kinds of Subjection, one due to an Uſurper, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther due to a rightful Owner of the Crown; for as theſe two Kings differ <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> in kind, ſo the Subjection due to the one doth differ <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> in kind, from what is due to the other. If you abandon this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, you juſtify the Cauſe of traiterous <hi>Abſolom,</hi> and his Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, againſt Innocent <hi>David</hi> and his Adherents; and there can be no ſuch thing as Uſurpation of Crowns and Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 2. <q>
                  <hi>Joaſh</hi> was firſt anointed and proclaimed, before any one ſtirred a Finger againſt <hi>Athaliah:</hi> Now this is a very different Caſe from raiſing Rebellions againſt a Prince, who is in the poſſeſſion of the Throne, to reſtore an ejected Prince, <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 34.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> Though <hi>Joaſh</hi> was firſt anointed and proclaimed King, before <hi>Athaliah</hi> was kill'd, yet it is plain, that the preparations to kill her, and the full purpoſe of their Mind ſo to do, were long before. And were theſe not ſo much as the ſtirring of a Finger againſt <hi>Athaliah</hi>'s Perſon, Crown and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57786:2"/>If the ſame kind of Subjection was due to <hi>Athaliah,</hi> a notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Uſurper, which was due to <hi>Joaſh</hi> the rightful Owner, (as you all along aſſert) then <hi>Jehoiada,</hi> and all the Godly and true Loyaliſts in <hi>Judah,</hi> were guilty of traiterous and wicked Conſpiracy. If not, then the grand Principle of your Book falls, and you ſhew your ſelf a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayer, rather than a Defender of true Loyalty and Allegiance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 3. <q>This of <hi>Athaliah</hi> was a peculiar Caſe; for God himſelf had entailed the Kingdom of <hi>Judah</hi> on the Poſterity of <hi>David,</hi> and therefore nothing could juſtify their Submiſſion to an Uſurper, when the King's Son was found, to whom the Kingdom did belong by a Divine Entail.—But, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <bibl>p. 35.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> It is plain from the Story, that the Nobles, Commons, and Clergy of <hi>Judah,</hi> did, out of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious Prudence and Reſpect to the Common Quiet, ſubmit to the Government of <hi>Athaliah,</hi> after they knew ſhe was an Uſurper, and that <hi>Joaſh</hi> the right Heir was in being, and preparation for the Crown, until they had by innocent Policy made themſelves ſtrong, and were ſufficiently prepared to depoſe and kill her; this their Submiſſion was juſt and laudable. And this Caſe doth ſtrongly prove, that a notorious Uſurper is to be ſubmitted to by all the People, when he cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and cut off without endangering the Common Quiet and Safety of the Realm; but when it can, with general Safety and Quiet to the Realm be effected, it is lawful and laudable to effect and accompliſh it. For though the Kingdom of <hi>Judah</hi> was a Theocracy, yet other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Kingdoms are not without Order and Government, agreeable to the general Rules of God's Word, and in that reſpect are a kind of Theocracy, though not in the <hi>ſtrict</hi> ſenſe: And it was upon Grounds and Reaſons common to other Nations and Kingdoms, that <hi>Athaliah</hi> was depoſed and killed, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe ſhe was a notorious Uſurper, and it was againſt the Common Quiet and Intereſt of the Realm, to bear with and ſubmit to her any longer. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi eadem ratio ibi eadem lex.</hi> It was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver God's intention to continue the Crown in the Poſterity of <hi>David,</hi> let them live as they liſt; but on ſuppoſition of their walking in God's Ways as <hi>David</hi> did: Which becauſe they did not, therefore God made <hi>Jeroboam</hi> King over ten Tribes, and afterward did alienate the Crown of <hi>Judah</hi> from the Houſe of <hi>David,</hi> to the <hi>Babylonians, Perſians, Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and <hi>Romans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 4. <q>If the Choice and Conſent of the People makes a Prince, then no Man is a Subject, but he who conſents to be ſo; for the major Vote cannot include my Conſent, unleſs I pleaſe; that is the Effect of Law, and Compact, or Force, not of Nature, <bibl>
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 24.</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> It was the Choice and Conſent of the greater part of the People, according to God's Word, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.14, 15. which made <hi>Saul</hi> the firſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57786:2"/>King of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Whoſe Election not being conſented to by ſome, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Scripture brands them for <hi>Sons of Belial,</hi> 1 Sam. 10.27. Here the major Vote did conclude the reſt. You cannot be a good Subject without your own Conſent; but a Subject you may be againſt your Will, tho the King be made by conſent of the People, according to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rules of God's Word; becauſe it is <hi>pro bono Publico,</hi> for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good, and abſolutely neceſſary for the uphold of Order, Unity, and Government among Men, that in ſuch Caſes the major Vote con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes all the reſt, the Light of Nature doth ſo dictate, and common Senſe allows it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 5. <q>If Subjects give their Prince Authority, they may take it away again if they pleaſe; there can be no irreſiſtible Authority deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the People: for if the Authority be wholly derived from them, who ſhall hinder them from taking it away when they ſee fit? Upon theſe Principles there can be no Hereditary Monarchy; one Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration can only chuſe for themſelves, their Poſterity having as much right to chuſe as they had, <bibl>
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 24.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> If indeed the People be the ſole principal Cauſe of conferring Authority upon the King, then they may take it away when they pleaſe, even as God himſelf doth. But this they are not, they are only Cauſes inſtrumental and ſubſervient, yet ſo neceſſary to the Being of juſt and legal Monarchy, that without their Conſent, Tacit, or Expreſs, no juſt Monarchy can begin and be ſounded. Yet will it not hence follow that the People may, at their pleaſure, recal the Authority which they have given; for being only Cauſes inſtrumental and ſubordinate, they can act nothing without the Concurence of God, the ſupream Cauſe and Governor of the World. But God doth oblige them to ſtick to, and abide by their King whom they have choſen, it is not in their Power to undo what they have done; they have bound themſelves by Oath and Covenant, Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit or Implicit, to their King, to be his Liege-men and Loyal Subjects, and a neceſſity lies upon them of keeping it; if they do not, they are perſidious. The Wife, by her own Act and free Conſent, gives Power to the Husband over her own Body, and to be her Head; and yet ſhe cannot unmarry her ſelf, and recal what ſhe hath done. Biſhops, as Cauſes inſtrumental under Chriſt, ordain Presbyters, and give them Miniſterial Authority; yet can they not therefore take it away at their pleaſure. The French Kingdom is Hereditary, and not Elective, and yet the Conſtitution thereof is ſuch, that Daughters cannot ſucceed to the Throne: if the French King ſhould go about to alter this Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without Conſent of the People, Would they think it any Injuſtice or Rebellion to reſiſt the invaſion of this their Fundamental Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? While the King upholds the Government, according to the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57786:3"/>Contract and Covenant between Him and the Nation, he may in no wiſe be reſiſted, tho he have his Authority from the People as God's Inſtruments; but if he go about to enſlave and ruin the Nation, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the original Contract and Covenant, it is no unlawful Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance for the Nation, by Force of Arms, to ſave it ſelf, and to withſtand the Invader and Deſtroyer of its Liberty, Rights, and Intereſt: For this is no reſiſting of Authority, but a juſt vindication of National Rights a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an Illegal Monarch, who pretends Authority, but really hath none, neither from God nor Man: For neither God nor Man gave him Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to be perfidious, and to enſlave and ruin the Nation, contrary to the Fundamental Oath and Covenant between Him and the People. It is this which is the Meaſure of his Authority; and this being extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, by his own perfidious violation of it, his Authority, as the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Conſequent thereof, muſt needs die and be extinct with it. Tho an Hereditary and Succeſſive Kingdom be not Elective, yet it is not a new Monarchy, but a continuation of the Old, which began by mutual Covenant, Tacit, or Expreſs, between Prince and People; and when this Foundation falls, the Government is diſſolved, and is no longer a juſt and legal Monarchy, but an Uſurpation and illegal Invaſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 6. <q>An Uſurper, by long continuance, may out-live thoſe who formerly wore the Crown; but does it give Right to him who has none, that he out-lives thoſe who had the Right? For though no Body elſe has any Right to the Crown, how does this make him a rightful King who has no Right? <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 24.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> It is allowed by all as a ſure Maxim, <hi>In aequali jure melior eſt conditio poſſident is,</hi> He who is in poſſeſſion of the Crown, hath ſufficient Right to it, when no one living hath better Right to it than he. If I find a Thing, and no one claims it, nor can the right Owner be found, it becomes mine by right of Occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation. He that was an Uſurper, ceaſes to be ſo by the deceaſe of the right owner. He is to repent in his own Breaſt and Boſom privately of his wrongful Intruſion: but the right Owner being dead, and all that claim under or by him, he is no longer an Uſurper, but rightful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 7. <q>The Revolutions of Government are not the Subjects Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but God's Prerogative, <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 43.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> There is no inconſiſtency between God's Prerogative and Subjects Duty in all Revolutions and Changes of Government, but Harmony and Concurrence. There was a great Revolution of Government in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they ceaſed to be governed by Judges, and the Order of Kings began: and yet in this famous Change, God as Principal, and the People as Inſtrumental, did concur in the Inſtitution of <hi>Saul</hi> for their firſt King. After his Death there was another great Revolution, though <hi>David</hi> by Divine Deſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57786:3"/>was immediately to have been King over all the Twelve Tribes, yet for ſeven Years the far greater part adhered to the Houſe of <hi>Saul,</hi> until God moved the Hearts of all the People unanimouſly to chuſe and ſubmit to <hi>David</hi> as their King. When the Lady <hi>Jane</hi> (who had the weaker Title) was proclaimed Queen of <hi>England,</hi> after the Death of King <hi>Edward,</hi> and was in poſſeſſion of the Throne, the Proteſtants in <hi>Suffock,</hi> out of conſcientious Loyalty, adhered to the Lady <hi>Mary,</hi> tho a Papiſt, and by their Means, as God's Inſtruments, ſhe acquired the Throne, and her Title prevailed as being moſt rightful. After the Death of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third the French King, there was a concurrence of God's Providence, and the Subjects Duty, in ſetting the King of <hi>Navarr</hi> in the Throne, though the greateſt part of the Nation had been againſt him, and had proclaimed another King, and bound them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a ſolemn League not to admit the King of <hi>Navarr,</hi> yet it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Right, at laſt it prevailed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 8. <q>There are but three Ways whereby God gives Kingly Power and Authority to any Perſons: Either by Nature, or by an expreſs Nomination, or by the Diſpoſals of Providence, <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 11.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> Nature by it ſelf, without Morality to rule and guide it, is a Beaſt or Machine, and therefore it can have no hand at all in the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Juſt and Law ful Kings. Nature and Morality differ, as the Horſe and the Rider, as the Pen and the Writer. Nature indeed, led, guided, and inſtructed by Morality, doth ſubſerve God the Governour of the World in the Inſtitution, uphold, and continuation of every Juſt and Legal Monarchy: but without it, Nature is blind and brutiſh in Things concerning Order and Government, both Divine and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, and therefore there never was nor can be a Lawful King by meer Nature diſtinct from Morality. Now all Morality is founded in Free-will and Rational Election, Choice and Conſent: And conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently every Juſt Monarchy, is founded in mutual Covenant, Tacit, or Expreſs, between the Prince on one part, and the People or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity on the other part, agreeably to the general Rules of God's Word, for the mutual Good of Prince and People, Ruler and Ruled. God's expreſs nomination of this or that Man to be King, obligeth all the People to own and ſubmit to him as their King, and him to conſent to be King over them; but till there be a mutual Conſent, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is not founded, it is but in preparation, if the major part con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, all the reſt are concluded, and are to be eſteemed Subjects of the Kingdom; and though the major part diſſent, yet having God's Word and expreſs nomination on his ſide, all the reſt owe Conſent, and may be compelled to it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 9. <q>Whether their preſent Majeſties have Legal Right to the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57786:4"/>Throne, is certainly needleſs in this Cauſe to diſpute, and ſerves only to confound it, by carrying Men into ſuch dark Labyrinths of Law and Hiſtory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as very few know how to find their way out again, <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 2.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> It is certainly neceſſary for juſtifying our ſwearing Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to them, that they have legal Right to the Throne; for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they have legal Right to it, they have no Right at all; and having no Right, they muſt needs be Uſurpers; and being ſo, it is only an equivocal Allegiance that can be due to them. But equivocal Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance will not ſuffice. <hi>Analogum per ſe poſitum ſtat pro famoſiori ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cato.</hi> The Law enjoining us to ſwear Allegiance to them, cannot in reaſon be thought to mean equivocal Allegiance, ſuch for kind as is due and payable to an Uſurper, but it muſt needs mean that kind of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance which is naturally due from Subjects to one that is rightful Prince before God and Men, and no Uſurper. And if there ſhould be any Ambiguity, or colour for ſcruple touching the Senſe of the Oath, it is abundantly cleared by this one thing, that the Law makers, by enjoining the Oath, muſt needs mean that kind of Allegiance which fully agrees with the Publick Prayers in the Liturgy, conſtantly uſed by the Law-makers, and impoſed upon all Conforming Miniſters, which is not equivocal Allegiance, but the ſame that was due and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id to Q. <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> K. <hi>James</hi> I, K. <hi>Charles</hi> I, and his Son ſucceſſively, <hi>viz.</hi> full and compleat Allegiance, without all Equivocation: For no one can uſe, ſay <hi>amen</hi> to, and heartily join in theſe Prayers for their preſent Majeſties, without All Hypocriſy and Deceit, who thinks them to have no legal Right to the Throne, that they are but Uſurpers. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Non-ſwearers, conſiſtently to their own Principle, refuſe to uſe the preſcribed Forms in the Liturgy for their preſent Majeſties, tho <hi>tantùm non,</hi> they admire the Liturgy. The Doctor by ſuppoſing it neeedleſs to diſpute whether their preſent Majeſties have legal Right to the Throne; and undertaking to prove that they have Right, tho no legal Right; that they have God's Authority, and yet no legal Right, doth greatly err: For there are but two kinds of Right, Legal or Evangelical. Evangelical Right doth not come into queſtion, for that is founded in Regeneration and Heavenly Adoption, and is wholly ſupernatural and inviſible. Either they have legal Right, or they have none: And it is plain they have, for it lies upon the Non-ſwearers to prove that they are manifeſt Uſurpers, which they can never do, but by carrying us into the dark Labyrinths of Law and Hiſtory, which can only confound, and ſerve to make plain things obſcure, but can prove nothing againſt their Majeſties Right.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 10. <q>We have no Example in Scripture, that any People were ever blamed for ſubmitting to the preſent Powers, whatever the Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57786:4"/>were, <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 21.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> We read of good King <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> that <hi>the Lord was with him, and he proſpered whitherſoever he went forth: and he rebelled againſt the King of</hi> Aſſyria, <hi>and ſerved him not,</hi> 2 King. 18.7. Now either this his Rebellion againſt the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> was ſinful be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, or it was not: If yea, then I ſee not how this Scripture can agree with it ſelf; for it doth manifeſtly imply, that God was with <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> and did proſper him in this his Rebellion againſt, and refuſal to ſerve the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> and ſo is the Opinion of the generality of Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters, who acquit <hi>Hezekiah</hi> from all Sin in this Matter, there being no Divine Obligation upon <hi>Hezekiah</hi> to ſerve and be tributary to the King of <hi>Aſſyria.</hi> If it was not ſinful, then here is an Inſtance of an honeſt and juſtifiable Rebellion againſt an Uſurping Power; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, had <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſubmitted to the Uſurpation of the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> he had been blame-worthy. <hi>Curſe ye</hi> Meroz, <hi>(ſaid the Angel of the Lord) curſe ye bitterly the Inhabitants thereof: becauſe they came not to the help of the Lord, to the help of the Lord againſt the Mighty.</hi> Judg. 5.23. It is plain from the Context, that King <hi>Jabin</hi> for twenty Years did mightily oppreſs <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and uſurp Dominion over them; and here the Inhabitants of <hi>Meroz,</hi> a City or Town in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> are curſed by the Angel of the Lord, for not concurring with <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Barak,</hi> and their Brethren the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> in warlike reſiſtance and oppoſition againſt the uſurping Tyrant and Oppreſſor <hi>Jabin.</hi> After <hi>Jeroboam</hi> had ſet up falſe Worſhip in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and caſt off the Lord's Prieſts from executing their Office unto the Lord, they, and after them, out of all the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſuch as ſet their Hearts to ſeek God, came to <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> to ſacrifice unto the Lord God of their Fathers. <hi>So they ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Kingdom of</hi> Judah, <hi>and made</hi> Rehoboam <hi>the Son of</hi> Solomon <hi>ſtrong three Years.</hi> 2 Chron. 11. Here the Subjects of King <hi>Jeroboam</hi> are prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Spirit of God for leaving him, and going over to King <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoboam,</hi> and taking part with him againſt <hi>Jeroboam;</hi> and conſequently they had been blameable if they had done otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 11. <q>Our Saviour's Argument relies wholly on the poſſeſſion of Power, <hi>Whoſe Image and Superſcription hath it?</hi> 
                  <bibl>p. 21.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> That our Saviour's Argument relies whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on Poſſeſſion, be it right or wrong, ſo as to oblige Men to pay the very ſame kind of Allegiance to a maniſeſt Uſurper, which is due to a moſt rightful King, (which is the principal point aimed at, and contended for by you) is not true. Our Saviour did not bring in any new Doctrine touching Sovereignty and Subjection, but by his Doctrine and Example taught every Soul to be ſubject to the Higher Powers, according as his Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> doth. But it was never the Apoſtle's meaning to confound the diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a notorious Uſurper, and one that is notoriouſly no Uſurper, but rightful King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God and all the World, as to Subjection and Allegiance. But though the preſent King ſhould be a manifeſt Uſurper, yet may nothing be attempted againſt his Perſon, Crown, and Government, which is againſt the Common Good and Quiet, when the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy will be worſe than the Diſeaſe; but where the Common Good and Quiet of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57786:5"/>Realm cannot be upheld without removing the Uſurper, there it is lawful and laudable to remove him, and to ſet the right Owner in the Throne; but it can never be lawful to do ſo by the right Owner; for Evil is not to be done that Good may come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 12. <q>Why ſhould we think the Apoſtle here intends a Diſtinction unknown to Scripture?—And let any Man judg in what Perplexities this Senſe of the Apoſtle's Precept would involve the Conſciences of Men? For theſe are great Diſputes among Learned Men, and how then ſhould Unlearned Men underſtand them? And I cannot think that the Reſolution of Conſcience, in ſuch Matters as all Mankind are concerned in, ſhould depend upon ſuch Niceties as Learned Men themſelves cannot agree in, <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 19.</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> Learning is an excellent Gift of God, and greatly ſerviceable to his Kingdom and Glory; but when deſtitute of Heavenly Wiſdom and Grace rightly to uſe it, it becomes the Devil's great Engine, whereby he upholds Atheiſm, Infidelity, Hereſy, Schiſm, Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, Superſtition, and falſe Religion in the World; and if Caſes of Conſcience concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Mankind muſt remain undecided, till all Learned Men be agreed about them, then there can be nothing certain in Religion; and Faith in Chriſt is no longer Faith in Chriſt, but the ſame with Scepticiſm and ungodly Dubitation, about Spiritual, Inviſible, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Things, which no Chriſtian can endure to hear. As in Divinity, though there be a thouſand Criticiſms reſpecting the Hebrew and Greek Text, Chronology, Genealogies, and Prophetick Expoſitions, wherein the Learned may ſafely differ, and yet Points of Faith, neceſſary to Salvation and holy walking with God, be all plain to ſuch as have the Spirit of Chriſt, even the moſt illiterate Men and Women: So though there be abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of leſſer Things in the Common and Statute-Laws of <hi>England,</hi> about which Judges, Lawyers, and Stateſmen themſelves may differ, yet ſtill there are ſome Maſter-Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and Foundation-Points of the Engliſh Government known to all; which being on all hands admitted not repugnant to God's Word, and to the Being of Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Humane Society in general, they are a ſufficient direction for the Conſciences of all in the Nation, ordinarily touching Subjection and Allegiance to the Higher Powers among us, and putting difference between a manifeſt Uſurper, and a manifeſt right Owner; and for extraordinary Caſes, the Nation is left to act <hi>pro re natâ,</hi> ſuitably to the Occaſion; and for extraordinary Evils, to provide extraordinary Cures; and in doubtful Caſes, to chuſe the ſafer Side: And therefore there is no neceſſity, that either we be all Slaves, according to your old Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance; or that all notorious Uſurpers be no Uſurpers, but rightful Kings before God, becauſe he permits Sin and Satan to ſet them in the Throne, according to your New Doctrine of Allegiance; which may ſerve for a job, and take with ſelf ſeeking Men, who guide themſelves by worldly Policy: but it can never ſink with honeſt and true Loyaliſts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 13. <q>The Titles of the Roman Emperors, for ſo many Ages toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, were either all of them ſtark naught, or the very beſt of them very doubtful, <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 20.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 14. <q>The four Monarchies were all as manifeſt Uſurpations as ever were in the World, and yet ſet up by the Decree and Counſel of God, <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 20.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> It is manifeſt as to <hi>Alexander</hi> the Founder of the Grecian Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, that he was no Uſurper, but a lawful Monarch: For he was (as all confeſs) lawful Monarch of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> before the inlargement of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions by Conqueſt. Now admit the worſt that meer Ambition, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful deſire of Empire, put him upon invading other Nations and Kingdoms; yet having won them by the Sword, upon their ſubmiſſion to him, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57786:5"/>under his Protection he became their lawful Monarch, and no Uſurper. Suppoſe alſo that the War of <hi>Julius Ceſar,</hi> againſt the Roman State and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, was unlawful, yet becoming Conqueror, and obtaining Conſent from the Senate and People of <hi>Rome,</hi> and being by Common Conſent created perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Dictator, from thenceforth he was no Uſurper, but lawful ſupream Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour; and if his Succeſſor, <hi>Auguſtus Ceſar,</hi> was not lawful Emperor, and no Uſurper, it cannot be told what lawful Empire is. The ſame may be ſaid of the other two great Monarchies, <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> and <hi>Perſian,</hi> for ought that can be proved to the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 15. <q>If Conqueſt gives a Right, then Force, the moſt unjuſt and violent Force, is right.—Submiſſion is only a forced and after-conſent, not to make a King, but to own him who has made himſelf King, and whom very often we would diſown and reject, were it ſafe to do ſo; and what Right can that give more than Force? <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 24.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> The Sword with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Submiſſion makes no Man legal King, but Submiſſion to the Conqueror upon legal Terms, is by the Law of Nations a juſt Foundation of legal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy: For it puts an end to War, and ſo introduceth Peace, Order, and ſettled Government: It is an act of rational Choice and Free-will; of two Evils ſet before us we chuſe the leſs, and either explicitly or implicitly cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with the Conqueror to be his Subjects, and he doth equally covenant with us to be our King and Protector.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 16. <q>What Right had my Anceſtors, three or four hundred Years ago, to chuſe a King for me? <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 24.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> They had juſt and true Right, by the Law of Nations, to lay the Foundation of an Hereditary Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy; otherwiſe there can be no ſuch thing as an Hereditary Monarchy, which no ſober Man will affirm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 17. <q>It is very abſurd to ſay, that the Right of Government is not derived from God, without the Conſent of the People, <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 25.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> It is very abſurd to make the People equal and coordinate with God in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Kingly Government; but no Abſurdity at all to make them ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate Cauſes, without whoſe Conſent there can be no ſuch thing as Juſt Monarchy; no more than it is to ſay, that God cannot make lawful Husband and Wife, without their own foregoing mutual Conſent. For though the Caſes widely differ in many things, yet in this they agree, that both are found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Conſent, and are not like the Relation between Parents and Children, which is founded in Nature, and natural Generation, and not in Conſent. If the People in conſenting, or diſſenting, tranſgreſs God's Law, that is their Sin, which God knows how to over-rule for his own Glory; and certainly he will ſo work in, diſpoſe, govern, incline, and change the Hearts, Minds, Wills, and Spirits of Men, that in ſpight of all Oppoſition there ſhall be a Church on Earth, and ſome degree of Civil Order and Government among
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57786:6"/>thoſe who are not of the Church. Now not only Church-Societies, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Civil Order and Political Government among Heathens, is neceſſarily ſounded in rational Choice and Conſent, and not in bruitiſh Motion, nor in natural Neceſſity, nor in extrinſecal Force and Violence. What harm can there be in this Poſition, that no Man can be rightful King without the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples juſt Conſent? Can God, who is infinitely Juſt, make a juſt and right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful King againſt the Peoples juſt Conſent? Then he is not himſelf, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 18. <q>In propriety of ſpeaking, there is no natural Prince but a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 11.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> Every King ſuppoſed rightful, is naturally a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Prince, and Allegiance is naturally due to him from all his Subjects; he is no Uſurper, but hath full Right to the Throne, according to the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of natural Light, common to Us and Heathens. Though he that is a Father, may be a Prince; yet no Father as ſuch can be a Prince, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no Father as ſuch can be a natural Prince: For if a Father as ſuch be a Prince, then every Father muſt needs be a King, and every Mother a Queen. But every rightful King is, in proper ſpeaking, naturally Prince and Sovereign over the People, and their Liege-Lord, whether he be a Father or not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 19. <q>
                  <hi>Hobbiſm</hi> is holding that Power holy gives Right: But my Doctrine is, That Power does not give Right, but is a certain ſign to us, that where God has placed and ſettled the Power, he hath given the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; therefore my Doctrine is not the ſame with <hi>Hobbiſm,</hi> 
                  <bibl>p. 15.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fut.</hi> Your Doctrine is the very ſame with <hi>Hobbiſm,</hi> becauſe you plainly confound Right and Wrong, moſt rightful and moſt wrongful Monarchs, and make them to be equally the Effects of God's Omnipotent Power and Providence; which is perfect <hi>Hobbiſm,</hi> and deſtructive of True Religion and Morality. If God's permiſſion of Might and Power to this or that Man, be a certain ſign to us, that God hath given him Authority and Right, then it unavoidably follows that Might and Right are inſeparable, and then all Murders, Treaſons, Robberies, Rapes, Sacriledges, Injuries, Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and unjuſt Violences, are for ever juſtified and legitimated, and there can be no ſuch thing as Good and Evil, Right and Wrong, Lawful and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 20. <q>The Outrages of Thieves and Pirats are very impertinently alledged in this Cauſe. They have Force and Violence, which every Man muſt ſubmit to, when he cannot help it; but Sovereign Power is God's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, though Princes may be advanced to it by no honeſter Means, than Thieves take a Purſe, or break open my Houſe, and take my Mony or Goods, <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 34.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> Though the Caſe of an Uſurper doth in many things greatly differ from that of Thieves and Pirats, yet in this they both agree, that neither hath true Right; the Divine Providence, by permitting
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57786:6"/>the Uſurper to be in the Throne, gives him no more Right to it, than his permitting a common Cut-purſe to ſteal my Mony, gives him Right to it. As we ſubmit to an High-way Robber, becauſe he is too ſtrong for us, and we cannot help it, ſo do we to an Uſurper. For I do not think you can name one M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n truly Loyal, that would ſubmit to a manifeſt Uſurper if he could help it. And if you ſuppoſe the Regnant Prince not to be manifeſtly an Uſurper, of neceſſity he is lawful and rightful Prince before God and all the World. For <hi>de non apparentibus &amp; non exiſtentibus eadem eſt ratio;</hi> things not plainly evident are to be eſteemed as not at all. And this doth prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally ſway with me as to the preſent Government. The great Law and Rule of Conſcience touching Allegiance, I take to be this, that whoever is in poſſeſſion of the Crown, compleat Allegiance is due to him, unleſs it be plain and evident to each Man's Conſcience, ſincerely ſtudious of his Duty to God and the King, that he is an Uſurper. But that their preſent Majeſties are ſo, is impoſſible to be proved. That an Hereditary Kingdom be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by a Monarch, is from God as Principal, and from the People as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental: but that it be governed by a notorious Uſurper, is from Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, and not from God, though God doth innocently permit it as he doth all other Sin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 21. <q>All Kings are equally rightful with reſpect to God, <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 14.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 22. <q>Nor does it make any difference in this Caſe, to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween what God permits, and what he does, <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 12.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> That all Kings are not equally rightful, with reſpect to God, is plain from God's own words; <hi>They have ſet up Kings, but not by me: they have made Princes, and I knew it not,</hi> Hoſ. 8.4. And from this undeniable Truth, that God is Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of Juſt Monarchy, but he is not Author of Uſurped Monarchy, it is contrary to his Holy Nature, and to his Holy Law; <hi>For thou art not a God that hath pleaſure in Wickedneſs,</hi> Pſal. 5.4. True it is, that God doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently permit Uſurpation, and his Permiſſion is not idle, but unſearchably operative: but ſtill he is no way Author of it; for Uſurpation is Sin, and God cannot be Author of Sin; to think it is Impiety, and to ſpeak it is Blaſphemy. So that all uſurping Kings are made by Satan, and not by God; and every time we ſay the Lord's Prayer in Faith, we do incluſively, and by implication, pray againſt uſurping Kings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 23. <q>The diſtinction then between a King <hi>de jure,</hi> and a King <hi>de facto,</hi> relates only to Humane Laws, which bind Subjects, but are not the neceſſary Rules and Meaſures of Divine Providence, <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 14.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> It relates to Divine Laws as Principal and Supream, and to Humane Laws as Subordinate and Inſtrumental: and all ſuch Humane Laws as are manifeſtly good, juſt, neceſſary and convenient for the Common Safety and Quiet, are in a large ſenſe rather Divine than Humane, though in a <hi>ſtrict</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:57786:7"/>ſenſe they are not Divine. The Divine Laws are the neceſſary Rules and Meaſures of our Duty, but not of God's Providence. For he permits all the Sins of Angels and Men contrary to his Holy Laws, and yet is no way Author of Sin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 24. <q>The Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is, That uſurping Kings, after they are once throughly ſettled in the Throne, are to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to as God's Ordinance, and compleat Allegiance is to be paid them as inveſted with God's Authority, whatever their Legal Right be. For the proof of which I appeal to Bp <hi>Overal</hi>'s Convocation-Book, <bibl>
                     <hi>p,</hi> 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> Not to diſpute whether Bp <hi>Overal</hi>'s Convocation. Book is to be admitted as an authentick and adequate Proof of the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that Book doth not prove your Point: For it proves only this, That uſurping Kings, when once throughly ſettled in the Throne, ceaſe to be Uſurpers, and become lawful Kings, and inveſted with God's Authority. This I grant; But doth this Convocation-Book ſay, that there can be a through ſettlement of Kings in the Throne without Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Right? This it ſaith not; and therefore you greatly err in replying up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that as a Proof, which really is none, but your own Miſtake and Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collection. You your ſelf confeſs <hi>pag.</hi> 9. That the foreſaid Convocation has not determined when a Government gotten by Uſurpation may be ſaid to be <hi>throughly ſettled.</hi> Now I affirm, in contradiction to the Scope and Tenour of your Book, that no Government can be <hi>thoroughly ſettled</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Legal Right. It is very probable that Convocation had in their Eye the two recent Caſes of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi> 1. As to <hi>Holland,</hi> while the King of <hi>Spain</hi> denied them to be a free independent and Soveraign State, and claimed them as his Right, and maintained his Claim by the Sword, and refuſed to treat with them as a Soveraign State; the Convocation might probably think, that the revolution in <hi>Holland</hi> was not throughly ſettled. But after King <hi>Philip,</hi> by his Agents, condeſcended to treat with them as a Sovereign State, and did ſo own and admit them, it is manifeſt, that from this time they began to be throughly ſettled; and though the begining ſhould be ſuppoſed to be by Uſurpation, yet now it ceaſed to be ſo, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a Juſt Government by the Law of Nations. 2. As to <hi>Scotland,</hi> while <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> was alive, though Priſoner in <hi>England,</hi> the Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation might perhaps doubt whether the Crown of <hi>Scotland</hi> might be ſaid to be throughly ſettled: but after ſhe was dead, there was no queſtion to be made of King <hi>James</hi> his right: for if it ſhould be ſuppoſed that he was an Uſuper before, yet after her Detth he had unqueſtionable Right, and began to be fully and throughly ſettled in the Throne, by the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and the municipal Laws of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:57786:7"/>
               <hi>Error</hi> 25. <q>To fight againſt a King, and not to fight for him, I think are two very different things; and when Kings make it impoſſible to fight for them, without fighting againſt the Religion and Liberties of our Country, they may thank themſelves, if their Subjects cannot defend them, <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 49.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> Either the King is rightful King, or he is not. If yea, then he is God's Ordinance; and how can we, in fighting for God's Ordinance, be ſaid to fight againſt it and true Religion? If not, then he is not God's Ordinance, and why then may we not fight againſt him, as <hi>Jehoiada</hi> and the good People of <hi>Judah</hi> did againſt <hi>Athaliah?</hi> You and your Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows think it your Vertue and Praiſe, that you had no hand in the late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution. Now, either the late King <hi>James,</hi> when the Prince landed, was rightful King, or he was not: If yea, then why did not you preach and preſs the Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance and Paſſive Obedience? Why did you not convince the People, that he who is not for his rightful King and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign is againſt him, and that to fight for him, is to fight for God's Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance? Why did you baſely and treacherouſly, both Clergy and Laity forſake him in his Diſtreſs, and ſtood looking on his Miſery, and afford him no help at all? Was this Loyalty to your King: Is it true Loyalty to be Neuter between God's Ordinance and Satan's Ordinance? But if the late King <hi>James</hi> when the Prince landed, was not rightful King, but an Invader and Subverter of the Legal Monarcy, and of True Religion, and National Rights and Liberties; and if the Prince came to ſave the Legal Monarchy, and to reſcue the National Rights and Liberties, and to preſerve and uphold True Religion, why ſhould it be your Vertue and Praiſe to have no hand in the Revolution?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 26. <q>To judg truly of the legality of the late Revolution, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires ſuch perfect skill in Law and Hiſtory, and the Conſtitution of the Engliſh Government, that few Men are capable of making ſo plain and certain a Judgment of it, as to be a clear and ſafe Rule of Conſcience, <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 2.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> Certainly either the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Undertaking, Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Progreſs in his Affairs to the time of his being ſet in the Throne by Common Conſent of the Nation, and the two Princeſſes, was Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, or we have done ill in giving ſuch ſolemn Thanks to God for it as we have; and not only we in this Nation, but <hi>Scotland,</hi> alſo and <hi>Ireland,</hi> as to the Proteſtant part, and all the Reformed Churches beyond Sea: and v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, of the Popiſh Party, even Princes and Sovereign-States have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> it. But too much Light puts out ſome Mens Eyes. It is ſufficient as to you, that nothing at all in the late Revolution came to paſs without the Providence of God: for this with you is all in all in pulling down and ſetting up of Kings, whether they have legal Right or not. As to the Non-ſwearer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the chief of them had a principal Hand in the late Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57786:8"/>and did eminently and publickly, by Word and Deed, and publiſhed Declaration, concur to it; and the thing it ſelf was ſo manifeſtly juſt, that it did overpower Mens Minds with its Evidence, and could not be gain-ſaid. Indeed there was for ſome time diſpute about the Point of Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication. But all the while it was indiſputably plain, that the Throne was empty, and the Government of the Nation for a time was unhinged, and the late King, by hearkening to Popiſh Counſels, and obſtinately relying upon them, had brought all this upon himſelf. The late Revolution needs not our Arguments to make it good, there is no neceſſity of turning over Volumes of Law and Hiſtory for deciſion hereof, it commends it ſelf to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Man's Conſcience, in the ſight of God, to be no proſperous Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but God's great Goodneſs and Mercy to three Proteſtant Nations, if we had but Grace to be thankful for it, and rightly to uſe and walk worthy of ſo great a Bleſſing; So great, that I greatly fear, what between the Non-ſwearers, and the deceitful and equivocal Swearers, and the mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious haters of Godlineſs and Holy unity among us, and the ſelf-ſeeking Spirit which ſo ſadly prevails, we ſhall yet have cauſe of renewing days of Faſting and Prayer, and happy we if we can ſo prevail with our God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 27. <q>If Princes receive their Authority from Men and Humane Laws, I cannot imagine, that their Power is any more than a Truſt, of which they muſt give an account to thoſe who have entruſted them with it, <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 36.]</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Confut.</hi> The Prince receives his Authority from God as Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal, and from the People as Inſtrumental; yet is he not ſtrictly accountable to us, but to God, as being God's Truſtee over us, and neither our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, nor our Equal, but Superiour to us all. Yet is he inviolably bound to perform Covenant with us, no leſs than we are bound to perform Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to him. If he ſhall, contrary to the fundamental Oath and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant between Him and the Nation, go about to enſlave us, to ſubvert the Legal Monarchy, and thoſe Laws by which the mutual Rights of Prince and People do conſiſt, he ceaſes to be our lawful King, and becomes the ſame with an Uſurper. We in ſo judging do not exerciſe any ſuperiority over him, nor call him to account, but as Men endued with common Senſe and Reaſon, we judg righteous Judgment. God himſelf permits us to judg be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and us: <hi>And now, O Inhabitants of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and Men of</hi> Judah, <hi>judg, I pray you, betwixt me and my Vineyard,</hi> Iſa. 5.3. Doth this make us ſuperiour to God? Do we, in diſcerning between Right and Wrong, and judging according to Truth, exerciſe Authority over God, and call him to account? Sure, Kings are not above God! while they have legal Right to the Throne, they may not be reſiſted: but if they have no legal Right to it, they may be reſiſted, as was <hi>Athaliah,</hi> when it can be done with Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Safety.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:57786:8"/>Many more Errors might be ſet down out of your Book, according to the old and true Maxim, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>no abſurdo dato, ſequuntur mille,</hi> grant one Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity, and a thouſand follow: But I have neither leiſure nor liſt to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with more, and had rather ſee their Majeſties unſubdued Enemies ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually reduced, and clothed with ſhame, and theſe three Nations freed from every Adverſary and evil Occurrent, and an end put to War, than read Books ſtuft with cold Arguments and dead Syllogiſms, to prove their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Majeſties now no Uſurpers, though lately they were, their Throne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now throughly ſettled. If really they were Uſurpers from the beginning, I doubt they are ſo ſtill. God hath indeed bleſſed his Majeſty with great Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs; but we are great Sinners againſt God, and engaged in a very expenſive War, againſt an Enemy not to be deſpiſed; and as we have ground to hope, ſo we have great reaſon not to be high-minded, but fear; for if we have not Succeſs, I doubt all Paper-Arguments, and artificial Syllogiſms, and Books of Diſpute, will prove too weak to convince Mens Minds that their preſent Majeſties are throughly ſettled in the Throne.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
